<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Burak Kürsad Günhan</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Burak Kürsad Günhan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018, Burak Kürsad Günhan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>90&#39;lar hep kalite veya &#34;survivorship bias&#34;</title>
      <link>/post/survivorship-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/survivorship-bias/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;meta property=“og:title” content=“90’lar hep kalite veya”survivorship bias&amp;quot;&amp;quot; /&amp;gt; Önce bazı youtube yorumları okuyalım. Başlığa ilham veren yorum:
Geçmiş özlemini daha açıklayıcı bi yorum
Ve tahmin ettiğiniz üzere bu yorumlar 90’larda piyasaya çıkmış şarkıların youtube videolarının altına yazılmış. Eminim bu tip yorumları siz de görmüşsünüz/dinlemişsinizdir. Acaba gerçekten de halkımızın sağduyusu bu konuda isabetli mi? Aslında kulağa çok mantıklı geliyor değil mi? Bi tarafta 90’ların şarkıları bi tarafta şimdi ne oldugu belli olmayan bir sürü şey?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The art of randomization</title>
      <link>/post/the-art-of-randomization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-art-of-randomization/</guid>
      <description>We all know that drugs are used as treatments for diseases, right? But did you think about how, scientifically, it is shown that drugs actually benefits and but not harms? Before my biostats education, I was naively imagining that since we know what causes the disease and which part of the body it affects etc., scientist are producing chemicals to cure the diseases. But, of course, this was so naive and human body is so complicated, and mostly we don’t know even the causes of the diseases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plane crashes and household furniture</title>
      <link>/post/plane-crashes-and-household-furniture/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/plane-crashes-and-household-furniture/</guid>
      <description>You may wonder what connects the plane crashes to household furniture, right? In both of those situations, there is a probability of dying attached to them. Maybe you already read stuff like 6 Things More Likely To Kill You Than A Plane Crash or this. You may see such news after a plane crash occurred in the world, and basically their take home message is that plane crashes is not that common as we might normally think.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confounding or the relationship between shoe size and salary</title>
      <link>/post/confounding-or-the-relationship-between-shoe-size-and-salary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/confounding-or-the-relationship-between-shoe-size-and-salary/</guid>
      <description>There are few terms in the context of statistics which I find very interesting and powerful when I, first, understand it. One of which is, undoubtedly, the concept of confounding. This term attracted my attention; since, in my opinion, it has potential to explain many mechanisms in different fields when statistical methods are used as tools. As you may imagine, medicine, biology or political science are only some examples for different areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nasıl &#34;reproducible research&#34; yaparım?</title>
      <link>/post/nas%C4%B1l-reproducible-research-yapar%C4%B1m/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nas%C4%B1l-reproducible-research-yapar%C4%B1m/</guid>
      <description>Diyelim ki bir arkadaşınız yaklaşık bir sene önce tamamlamış olduğunuz bir research calışmanızdan birşey sordu. Calısmanıza dönüp analizleri tekrar gözden geçirmek, tablo ve figürleri reproduce edebilmeniz ne kadar vaktinizi alacaktır? Veya arkadaşınızı boşverin, sadece kendiniz 2 sene önce hazırlamış olduğunuz sunumdaki resultlarin tekrar elde etmeye calışsanız? Bu süreyi ve olası zahmeti azaltmanın (ve daha fazlası) metodu reproducible research yapmanız!
Eğer günlük hayattaki calışmalarınızda bir sekilde data analysis yapıyorsaniz, eski yontemler yerine reproducible research kullanmaniz belki biraz daha zahmetli ama uzun vadede kesinlikle daha faydali.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A misunderstanding about life expectancy</title>
      <link>/post/a-misunderstanding-about-life-expectancy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-misunderstanding-about-life-expectancy/</guid>
      <description>Here I want to talk about a very common mistake when it comes to life expectancy and its interpretation. In one of my epidemiology courses, the lecturer showed the below Figure.
I am sure you also see graphs like that not this particular one (I mean for Switzerland) but maybe similar. OK, we see a very clear trend that life expectancy increasing in the last century. It was even doubled, right?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>